2
The "New" Ideology in the 1960s

[UNCTAD] will show whether the developed countries are capable of discharging the obligations imposed on them by their wealth. It will also require them to renounce their traditional policy of passively accepting the supremacy of market forces. Against blind respect for those forces and against the trade restrictions imposed by the strongest against the weakest ranges the new ideology which inspired the convening of the conference. That ideology . . . will constitute a new phase in the age old struggle for the liberation of peoples and respect for human dignity.

— Alphonso Patino of Colombia, 1963

. . . the developing nations want change. They want a "new" international division of labor. They want and have a "new" trade forum. They want "new" trade principles. They want new and different techniques of aid, not necessarily at the sacrifice of the old but in addition to what is now being done.

— Sidney Weintraub of the United States, 1964(1)

Even though the decade began with signs that the Bretton Woods system could be reformed in favor of third world interests, the sixties were marked by growing economic divisions between north and south. LDCs became more aware of how their interests clashed with those of the DMCs. From 1960 through 1965 evidence mounted that poorer nations received few of the benefits the liberal system had promised. Developed countries enjoyed most of the growth induced by trade. Trade favoritism among already industrialized states continued. Third world leaders saw such continuing abuses as proof that the postwar system merely continued prewar relations in a new form. The LDCs, united under the ethic and analysis developed since the war, pushed for creation of a new international economic system dedicated to that new ideology.

In the first five years of the decade the ideology itself developed only along the lines already established in the 1950s. Third world economic analysis became more complex in response to new issues. Prebisch's framework allowed the south to apprehend and explain growing income and trade "gaps" between rich and poor nations. Third world governments proposed an array of new policies to increase their share of global trade. They suggested specific public aid targets, multicommodity pricing agreements, compensatory financing for trade income shortfalls, and special aid for the least developed LDCs (LLDCs), especially the new states in Africa. All of these new economic proposals attacked similar problems, consequences of the Bretton Woods system that no one who created the system had expected, or that none had expected would have such distressing effects on poorer nations.

By mid-decade the ideology had begun to change in fundamentally new ways. Adherents had developed a new self-awareness and self-confidence. They stopped calling for reforms and started calling for a new economic order. They had become aware of the ideology they shared and aware that the ideology outlined a plan for a new economic system. They knew that plan was not complete; for example, the ellipsis in Patino's comment stands in place of a long remark that the ideology had to be specified further. In the sixties, for the first time, third world officials began to pursue the development of their ideology consciously.

In the middle of the decade the ideology's adherents developed a specific political identity as the Group of 77. The agreement on a formal political identity triggered the alliance's development of its first political theory, explicit views about strategy and tactics which had not been part of the third world's shared position before. The southern allies insisted on using what they called "democratic means" to achieve their ends. They understood such means to include majority or consensual rule by national governments voting as equals, as well as the use of persuasion to influence legislative and public opinion in the wealthy states.

Later, third world leaders would learn from the failure of this initial strategy. As a result of their failures in the sixties, they would know how to exploit the DMCs' economic vulnerabilities in the early 1970s when the Bretton Woods system began to create problems even its key members felt.

In the 1960s, however, not only had the LDCs not yet agreed upon the political strategies needed to exploit the vulnerabilities that would appear when the Bretton Woods system started to break down; there were few hints that such a breakdown would ever occur. The system was in its heyday. It was brilliantly achieving the goals its founders had set for it. The cover of the GATT's 1966 annual report makes the point well with its graphs of indices of international trade and world production from 1956 to 1966.(2) Both rise dramatically, trade volumes leading the way for production. The liberal system assured the truly unprecedented global prosperity that marked the sixties. For the wealthy market states, unlike for the poorer ones, few unanticipated problems appeared in the sixties to make them doubt the viability and value of the system which had spurred the unprecedented growth.

One unanticipated development in the sixties, indirectly connected to the system's success, created as many opportunities for the third world alliance as it did problems. But the new order ideology, as it existed then, did not give the alliance the theoretical means of fully resolving the problems while fully exploiting the opportunities. The vast increase of new sovereign states provided the alliance with many more members and thus increased the political importance of the emerging ideology. But the interests and frustrations of the new states differed from those of states that had been independent longer. Some of the new states said that rich nations had duties to poor nations because colonizers had historical duties to the colonized. This ethic based on historical obligations clashed with earlier third world notions about the permanent rights and duties of states. This difference of opinion contributed to the failure of the Group of 77's first political strategy by reducing the impact of attempts to present a united front in order to influence opinion in developed countries. This disunity, however, left a fortuitous legacy for the south: The unity of the third world behind the New International Economic Order in the early seventies caught many in the north by surprise.

The part of the story of the new order ideology told in this chapter ends before the third world reaffirmed its unity. It begins with the trade issues the founders of Bretton Woods failed to anticipate and shows how those emergent issues led to the first UNCTAD, the formation of the Group of 77, and the first southern calls for a completely "new" economic system. The second section discusses the political analysis the group adopted in the latter half of the decade. The third and final section relates how other unanticipated consequences of the system, first apparent in the sixties, led to the developments in third world economic policy analysis at the end of the decade. It also discusses the differences in third world opinion that then were current, linking them both to the different problems experienced by different third world states as a result of the system's operation and to the incomplete incorporation of the newest states into the alliance.

From Trade Issues to the Group of 77

As would be expected of the international organization most concerned with trade matters, the GATT was the first institution to make the international community aware of trade related global income "gaps." It did so in 1960 by suggesting explanations for problems others had previously identified but not explained. In 1958 Nehru had used postwar national income statistics to demonstrate a widening income gap between rich and poor nations.(3) By 1959 it had become commonplace for some news magazines in worldwide circulation to identify the north-south division of the globe as more critical than the east-west division. (4) Nonetheless, in the late fifties, when aid rather than trade issues still dominated the north-south agenda, officials and commentators rarely correlated the increasingly apparent income gap with recent developments in international trade. Of course, throughout the fifties third world leaders recognized that higher returns from trade could increase their national wealth; that is why they proposed some new trade policies, then compensatory financing for trade shortfalls, and finally even resurrection of the entire ITO.(5) But actual figures on the third world's declining proportion of both world trade and world income first became available in 1960 through a report circulated by the GATT.(6) The highly correlated figures suggested that the third world's declining proportion of world trade caused its declining proportion of world income.

GATT did not draw the causal connection from the related trends. But third world leaders increasingly did draw that connection by following, in part, the Prebisch thesis. Most southern leaders first gave the implications of the Prebisch argument serious consideration only when the trade-related income gaps became apparent. Third world representatives to the U.N. carefully discussed different ways that nonmarket forces might be keeping the prices of DMC manufactured goods relatively high. Some called for establishing countervailing influences on the world market in order to keep LDC prices high as well. The poorer oil producing states formed OPEC and justified it to the United Nations General Assembly as an institution designed to keep oil prices high. (7) (Ironically, they did not succeed in their stated purpose until 1973.) In 1960 the Colombian delegate spoke to the General Assembly's economic committee about establishing "trade unions" of raw material producers.(8) As if to capitalize on these developments, in 1961 ECLA republished Prebisch's seminal study.(9)

Just as in the 1950s when some third world officials used parts of Prebisch's theory to understand and respond to trade problems created by cold war stockpiling policies, once again few third world officials completely adopted Prebisch's explanation of the trade and income gaps. Instead of focusing directly on the powers of the firms and unions in developed nations, most representatives of individual third world governments talked about the flaws in the postwar trade system that the Haberler report to the GATT outlined. Third world officials saw the relative decline in their income from trade as a reflection of the fact that wealthy market states had been able to mold the liberal system to their needs. The trade system, they noted, tended to allow DMCs to trade industrial products among themselves freely while forcing LDCs to pay tariffs on the same items. And the system allowed the north to erect protectionist barriers to southern imports.(10)

Only when the poorer nations turned to solutions to the apparent trade problems did they line up behind the Prebisch thesis rather than Haberler's. The LDCs never called for a return to the GATT' s laissez faire principles; instead, the south continued to call for conscious adoption of global trade policies that would increase third world income, policies justified by their view of the rights and duties of states. As a Uruguayan official put it in 1960, in place of the GATT's "equal treatment" principle, which allowed richer nations greater power to influence economic relations than poorer nations (even before special concessions like those to the European Community had been made), there should be a principle of "equitable treatment," international policies aimed at fostering the trade relations appropriate to each nation's level of economic development and its development goals.(11) In particular, beginning in 1961 and following a set of proposals made by Africa's newly independent, most populous state, Nigeria, the third world demanded a system of generalized tariff preferences for third world goods.(12)

This new policy proposal did not fundamentally change the emerging third world economic ideology. Adherents simply added the new version of the trade issue and new proposed solution to other policy analyses already in the ideology. At the first conference of nonaligned countries in Belgrade in September of 1961 not only did the delegates condemn the postwar aid system for the way it linked cold war goals to development goals, they condemned the trade system as well. Delegates called on the developed nations to improve the terms of trade for LDC goods and to end restrictive trade practices that harmed poorer states.(13) At the same time, southern spokesmen in the U.N. reaffirmed their ethic and their central economic goal as keys to abolishing the trade and income gaps. As the Bolivian delegate put it, "Each society has its own needs and its own means to satisfy them. But if the underdeveloped countries wish to survive they must industrialize."(14)

By 1961 even the GATT was calling for the industrialization of the third world as one means for dealing with the poorer nations' declining share of world trade. In a special study of trade and development for its Annual Report, the GATT Secretariat analyzed possible ways to ease the relative decline. It found little room for expanding traditional exports and advocated industrialization along the model of the Latin American Free Trade Area instead. That model required that national specialization in particular industrial lines become an object of intergovernmental cooperation in each of the developing regions. The GATT even raised the possibility that intervention to raise the terms of trade for traditional exports might prove worthwhile in the short run, although it did not discuss specific ways to accomplish such intervention.(15)

Continuing GATT interest in the declining relative volume of third world trade reflected the fact that liberal economists treated the problem as a real dilemma. Most felt that in the long run terms of trade would swing in favor of food and raw materials (rather than manufactured goods) under the influence of diminishing returns. Because raw materials exist only in limited quantities, they should become scarcer, costlier to extract, and, thus, relatively more costly as time goes on.(16)

Liberal economists may still be right, in the long run. But in the 1960s, predictions based on facile analysis of the long run availability of raw materials proved wrong. Instead of rising, the value of third world raw material exports relative to northern manufactures fell. That fact could be explained (without rejecting the liberals' long run conclusions) by pointing to the different manipulations of the world market by unequally powerful states. The already rich benefited the most from such manipulations. At least that was the conclusion both the GATT and a significantly large group of third world officials accepted. What to do about it was another matter.

Just as the LDCs remained committed to their vision, the GATT Secretariat remained committed to liberal trade. The GATT's commitment precluded it from serving as a framework for the sorts of policies third world governments preferred to use to combat the trade and income gaps. In the early sixties they began to look for other organizational frameworks.

In 1962 the Cairo Second Afro-Asian Conference called for a United Nations trade conference to provide an international forum outside GATT for proposals like commodity pricing agreements, compensatory financing, and a generalized system of tariff preferences. The U.N. votes of the governments represented at the Afro-Asian conference, along with the votes of those Latin American states which had been invited observers and of socialist governments who wanted the U.K. conference to deal with ways to expand east-west trade, assured that the first United Nations Conference on Trade and Development (UNCTAD I) would be called quickly. The General Assembly scheduled the conference for late spring of 1964.(17)

In the months between the Cairo conference and UNCTAD third world frustrations over the effects of the postwar economic system coalesced. In addition to the problems of cold war-related aid policies and the GATT's obviously inadvertent function as an agency sanctioning DMC protectionist policies, other issues had been festering.

In the third world view, despite the creation of the IDA and the Special Fund, the World Bank and bilateral aid donors had consistently exacerbated the gap between rich and poor states by loaning only to the richest of the poor.(18) The IDA itself remained only a poor second-best alternative to SUNFED because the IDA adopted the World Bank's system of voting weighted in proportion to wealth, rather than the one nation, one vote system SUNFED would have followed. Dissatisfaction with the aid system even convinced the majority in General Assembly to set official targets for aid to third world countries, to define one of the duties of the wealthy states throughout the development decade more explicitly as the duty to give 1 percent of their GNPs to poorer states, a goal few wealthy states ever reached. The UNRRA goal for grants to needy nations, which some poorer states could say that they themselves had respected, provide the precedent for the 1 percent figure. Those unusual LDCs that had received significant aid since the second world war, such as India, complained about the burden that repaying those debts placed on an economy still trying to catch up with the wealthy states, the problem the IDA was supposed to solve.(19)

Even the Bretton Woods monetary system came under third world attack in the months leading up to UNCTAD I. According to the south, the wealthy countries controlling the monetary system were the only nations that could afford to make their currencies convertible. The major evidence LDCs offered for that assertion was the fact that it took nearly a decade and a half of internationally supported postwar economic development before western European states wanted to make their money convertible. For those states that could afford them, convertible currencies made it easier trade, at least with other countries that had convertible currencies. The fact that LDCs could not yet afford convertibility meant that developed countries would be more likely to increase their trade with each other than they would be to increase their trade with LDCs. Given the LDCs' views about the rights and duties of states, they placed the blame for this situation on the postwar monetary system, which had enshrined the principle of convertibility, and not on themselves. The European precedent suggested, after all, that poorer nations should not be expected to live up to the monetary rules the postwar system demanded.

Despite this criticism, the postwar monetary system was the object of much less third world scorn in the early sixties than either the trade or aid systems. Third world spokesmen even praised the IMF in 1963 for establishing a system of short term loans that could be taken out by countries suffering losses in expected income due to sudden drops in the prices of commodities they exported. Still, the LDCs chastised the IMF for limiting this financing to an amount that would bring export earning up to a longer term trend, a trend that third world governments believed was declining for almost any commodity they exported.(20)

In light of these mounting grievances, when the Egyptian delegate began the General Assembly debate on economic matters directly after the Second Afro-Asian Conference had ended in Cairo, he summarized a history of frustrations going back to the Marshall Plan and UNRRA. He said that significant international systems for aid to DMCs, systems which took into account those countries' own definitions of their economic needs, had existed for years. Those systems, developed to aid postwar Europe, had never been copied in giving aid to Asian, African, and Latin American countries. Most significantly, similar consideration of third world nations' self-defined economic needs never took place.(21)

By June of 1963 the nations that would become the Group of 77 had formally outlined their UNCTAD positions through a series of regional meetings. At those regional conferences third world leaders turned their frustrations with the postwar economic system into a call for "a new international division of labor," a division that would no longer make the third world the world's "hewers of wood and drawers of water," the south said, using a Biblical phrase that already had long history in the literature on imperialism before 1963.(22) The "new international division of labor" simply meant that the third world should become industrialized.

In 1964 this call for a whole new international economic system was no doubt more symbolic than practical. Even if they had had the power to create a new economic order, third world governments still did not have the plan. The regional third world meetings came up with outlines of a new global system of production no more coherent or complete than any of the others the third world had presented since the war. The regional meetings simply reiterated the reform proposals that third world states had long supported. The call for a "new" world economy was more a way of symbolizing the increasing significance that third world governments attached to their proposals in the months before UNCTAD.

Plans offered in the months before UNCTAD even differed a bit from region to region throughout the third world. The Latin American states emphasized that those nations that had benefited the most from the postwar economic institutions had the greatest duty to aid other nations. Latin America also placed solutions to debt servicing problems in one of the most prominant positions in its plan.(23) African states identified former colonies as the most needy states and gave special emphasis to calls for tariff preferences to be given to the least advantaged nations. While the Latin American resolution mentioned that proposal it placed it lower on the agenda simple because a smaller proportion of the Latin American states could be called "least advantaged" by any definition. The Africans also called for multi-commodity pricing agreements that would allow funds collected while protecting the ceiling price of one commodity (by selling from a buffer stock) to be used to defend the floor price of another commodity.(24) This was another policy discovered among the many never-enacted suggestions left by Lord Keynes. (25) Latin American and Asian delegates failed to consider it until the Africans brought it up at the joint meeting of the regions prior to UNCTAD.

Asians, Africans, and Latin Americans easily reconciled the differences in their draft proposals by invoicing the principles they had developed in the forties. Both the debt problem, of special interest to the richest LDCs in Latin America and Asia, and the problems associated with stabilizing and increasing the prices of the weakest commodities traded, issues especially important to Africa, had to be included as issues to be addressed by the "new" world economic order. Each problem reflected a major impediment in the development paths particular sovereign states had chosen.

Third world unity behind shared principles increased in the months leading up to the first UNCTAD. Third world governments repeatedly emphasized the duty of each state to support the economic development programs chosen by other states. Third world spokesmen even asserted that this principle explained part of the value of their new ideology. They called the ideology a contribution to global economic development. Echoing Patino, who had made the statement at the head of this chapter the week before, a Libyan delegate explained to the General Assembly's economic committee in 1963 that third world states had discharged their development duties toward others by contributing a new, higher set of moral values to the development debate.(26) Along with Patino, the Libyan represented the general opinion of southern officials when he stated that the new ideology was an historically unique, valuable contribution to humanity.

At the first UNCTAD southern governments acted on the basis of their self-perceived moral leadership to have the conference approve their ethic and their analysis of the world economy. Before the meeting Raul Prebisch, who had been elevated from ECLA to be Secretary General of the UNCTAD in 1963, provided a new, more extensive gloss of his theories and a set of policy recommendations in a report entitled "Toward a New Trade Policy for Development." This report became the informal agenda for the conference.(27) The conference approved resolutions both restating the report's policy proposals and affirming bits of Prebisch's analysis. The resolutions called these proposals and assertions "trade principles" that would guide the "new and just world economic order" the conference intended to create. (28) All these principles had appeared earlier, outgrowths of the Havana Charter debates, the Panch Shila, assertions about the validity of Prebisch's analysis of trade, and the special demands that each third world region made directly before UNCTAD I.

Many governments rejected the third world's self-proclaimed moral leadership and the principles embodying it, but even at the first UNCTAD northern opponents to the south's call for a new order were divided. With fewer than three other partners, the United States voted against five of the third world's fifteen "general" principles. Those principles all affirmed parts of the third world view of the economic rights and duties of states -- the principle of the equality of states, the principles stating that trade and development were global concerns, and ones saying that every state had the right to choose its own economic system and control the natural resources within its boundaries. The U.S. was a minority of one opposing a principle that disarmament should be undertaken to free funds for development. Between four and nine other DMCs joined the U.S. when it opposed approving international commodity agreements, "equitable treatment," and development goals for the IMF. Britain and Australia alone opposed a principle that colonized nations should be given special development consideration.

No one opposed five other principles. Two referred to other special targets for development, the LLDCs and landlocked areas. Two more referred directly to the issues that triggered the calls for UNCTAD in the first place. DMCs agreed that their own moves toward economic integration, including the European Community, should not harm LDCs, and all states agreed that similar regional trade groups among LDCs should be allowed. The final principle approved without dissent was the abstract goal of the conference, movement toward a new international division of labor.(29)

These votes determined how the Group of 77 would interpret the results of the conference. While many DMCs opposed the group's practical suggestions for increasing third world income from trade, the U.S. could be singled out as the major opponent to the even more fundamental third world principles. That meant there was little hope for the immediate future, in spite of all the bright talk about the "development decade" that had marked the end of the fifties. Immediately after UNCTAD I most third world spokesmen identified the U.S. as the primary author of the postwar system, the system's major beneficiary, and the major reason that fundamental reform of the system was impossible.

Such an assessment may have been too harsh. American opposition to some of the south's principles may only have reflected misunderstanding of the south's views. Sidney Weintraub, one of the American delegates, wrote after the conference that its "Final Act" (the document containing the fifteen principles) did not necessarily reflect what was in the minds of all those at the conference. That is certainly true. But the "Final Act" did reflect the ideology that Asian, African, and Latin American representatives to global economic meetings had been developing for twenty years; earlier third world positions provide a good guide to what was in the minds of southern delegates at UNCTAD; The history of the new order ideology suggests a slightly different understanding of "real" third world concerns than the one Weintraub offered.

Weintraub considered the third world proposals basically self-serving. He felt that the principles opposed by the U.S. were designed to let LDCs unfairly claim some of the current wealth some developed states had earned. To him the Group of 77's position appeared doubly unfair because it seemed to demand much less from the socialist states than from the DMCs.(30) Both judgements can be questioned even though they logically follow from American premises at the time.

One American premise was that the rules of international economic conduct had been long established and accepted by all nations. Yet in 1964 the the Bretton Woods system had only been operating as it had been intended to for five years and its rules had never been accepted by the majority of states at UNCTAD. The south still acted in 1964 the way the U.S. had in 1944, as if the best structure for international economic relations had yet to be discovered and agreed upon.

A second U.S. premise was that the LDCs goal of a "new" order was just a new way to express an old-fashioned state interest in aggrandizment at the expense of others. Yet the more complex third world goal remained as it had been in the 1940s; southern states wanted to establish an international economic system based on permanent national development rights and responsibilities. By 1964 the relative poverty of the third world convinced its leaders that, under their own principles, they were no longer required to materially aid other states. Their responsibilities were limited to things like promulgating their twenty-year-old "new" moral values within the U.N., values that (while self-serving in the short term) were considered a real contribution by many in the south. (31) Southern aid and trade proposals in 1964 no more envisioned reducing the wealth of the DMCs than the U.S. UNRRA proposals in 1944 envisioned reducing the wealth of Latin American contributors. Rather, both sets of proposals aimed at assuring that a specific region of the globe would be able to produce a greater proportion of the new wealth constantly created by the world economy. The UNCTAD proposals especially aimed at giving the third world more of the globe's trade-induced growth, something the LDCs seemed to have lost to the DMCs since the war.

In contrast, given American premises, the UNCTAD proposals had to be seen as nothing other than a challenge to the only legitimate order in the world economy. They had to be understood as part of the LDCs' strategy in a worldwide zero sum game in which their economic gain was the DMCs' economic loss and in which the DMCs' economic loss was the political gain of their greatest rival, the communist bloc.

Given the nature of the south's grievances, which predated the cold war, the American tendency to understand the results of UNCTAD in east-west terms disturbed most southern delegates. Nonetheless, at the first UNCTAD the second and third worlds were clearly allies. The socialist governments' goal at the meeting was to, "air their grievances against import-export restrictions and discriminatory cold war policies imposed upon them by the developed countries."(32) Throughout the conference socialist states seemed to accommodate third world demands that they expand their trade with the south, thus making it appear that the east-south agreement could extend further than the conference floor.(33)

The depth of the increasing ideological rift between first and third worlds can be seen by comparing Weintraub's image of the new system that third world governments wanted to create to the image of the postwar system held by the most radical third world governments. The extreme northern (e.g., U.S.) and southern views had come to resemble the "mirror images" that the superpowers had of each others' aims. Like cold war mirror images, the views of the extreme states in the north and south assured ongoing misunderstanding.(34) The most radical third world states viewed the postwar system as a deliberately engineered mechanism for exploiting poorer nations' property, just as the U.S. saw the proposed system as a deliberately engineered mechanism for exploiting developed nations' property. Both extremes even understood the role of the socialist states in the same way. While Weintraub viewed the Group of 77 as unfairly excusing the socialist states from the group's wealth-grabbing scheme, some third world leaders viewed DMC moves in the sixties toward expanding east-west trade as ways of integrating the socialist countries into the unfair expanding trade system as equal partners and thus leaving the third world, the only exploited region, with an even smaller proportion of the world's trade.(35)

Due in part to the fruitless ideological battle between mirror images at UNCTAD, one of the more interesting, deeper conflicts between the Group of 77 and the United States hardly appeared: the conflict between the assumed primacy of the rights of property owners that underlies laissez faire doctrine and the assumed primacy of national governments in defining property rights that stands on the surface of the third world's interpretation of the economic rights and duties of states found in the U.N. Charter. Even in 1964 there may have been some ground for compromise between north and south on this fundamental point. In practice, northern states balanced the claims of property owners against other national interests as much as LDCs, in practice, balanced their advocacy of the principle of sovereignty against their other interests.{36 ) The UNCTAD debate forced neither north nor south to consciously recognize that they balanced their property principles with other concerns, and did so in much the same way. The UNCTAD debate did not even require them to discuss such fundamental, substantive concerns.

At the UNCTAD meeting the most fully and fruitfully discussed conflicts between north and south occurred not over principles but over specific trade policies and trade theory. Unlike in the debate over principles, in discussions of those topics most DMCs shared the same views.

At the level of practical trade policy north-south differences had abated somewhat even before UNCTAD I, and afterward they continued to abate throughout the decade. The IMF's creation of a compensatory financing facility illustrates the early move toward greater agreement. Elevation of UNCTAD from a temporary conference to a permanent institution of the United Nations created the structure in which commodity agreements could be negotiated. Nonetheless, the African proposal for multicommodity agreements remained dormant throughout the decade, although the IMP began to investigate ways that its resources might be used to finance buffer stocks.(37) In addition, the wealthier members of the GATT gradually accepted the principle of granting tariff preferences to developing nations. It took until the 1970s before many states passed the legislation that would actually allow such preferences to be awarded.(38)

None of these developments on the level of practical policy represented any widespread DMC acceptance of the empirical trade theory underlying the Group of 77's trade demands. The IMF's compensatory financing facility remained committed to the notion that long run trends in the world market represented fair prices. Rich states justified generalized tariff preferences as a new form of foreign aid, not as step required to increase third world trade income because it had been declining due to the powers of companies in DMCs to control world market prices. Even though the GATT Secretariat had provided evidence of the decline in the LDCs' proportion of world trade prior to the first UNCTAD, the GATT did not accept the theory that there was a trade-related "income gap" that prevented the LDCs from achieving their development aims. After the first UNCTAD, the GATT Secretariat reported that Prebisch's measure of this "gap" per se meant nothing because of the differences in export needs among LDCs. These differences made it impossible that any theory claiming to explain trade problems could be applied to the entire group of nations.(39)

On the surface, the GATT position on the trade gap seems to say nothing more than Weintraub's observation after the first UNCTAD that the trade gap was not necessarily a fact just because the majority of delegates at UNCTAD voted to say it was.(40) But the GATT position, unlike Weintraub's, can be linked directly to Gottfried Haberler's critique of Prebisch's theory. Haberler's 1958 GATT report condemning the DMC protectionist policies argued that such policies could cause the terms of trade for specific third world goods to decline, but he went on to argue that it was impossible to weigh the effects of extra-market interventions on world prices as a whole. The protectionist policies still employed by the LDCs might be counteracting the effects of DMC policies or the LDC policies might even be improving the terms of trade for some of their goods over the real, free market trend. Case by case analysis would be needed in order to determine the actual effects of these interventions. Until such analysis was undertaken, Haberler felt this aspect of Prebisch's argument should not be accepted as proven. Haberler also argued that it seemed paradoxical to expect that the terms of trade for so many diverse commodities as those sold by third world producers would all have the same trend at the same time; again he advocated more detailed study of individual cases than the Prebisch reports offered.(41)

The GATT was right that major differences among LDC economies existed in the sixties. The Group of 77 certainly recognized that, at least in its attempt to assure that each state's particular concerns become part of the alliance position. But the GATT implied that the differences among third world states provided sufficient reason for them to support the ultimate creation of a world with no trade restrictions. The south rejected that implication. At UNCTAD meetings and the international conferences between them, third world governments continued to view the terms of trade problem as one they all shared and as one that could not be eliminated simply by moving toward a more open trading system.

The Group of 77's Politics

After the first UNCTAD failed to lead to major changes in global economic regimes, the Group of 77 emphasized political victories rather than ones in the realm of economic policy. The group pointed to accomplishments like the establishment of rules for further north-south discussions and the creation of the group itself. In fact, southern officials considered the institutionalization of the third world alliance to be the most important thing UNCTAD achieved.(42) In terms of the history of the NIEO ideology that is certainly true. The institutionalization of the Group of 77 marked the beginning of the third period in the ideology's development, the first period in which the third world alliance developed its own political analysis.

UNCTAD I's hottest debate had made the group extremely concerned with unity. DMC proposals that voting in the conference be weighted according to trade wealth caught Asian, African, and Latin American delegates off guard. There was nothing new in this request. DMCs were only reaffirming the political principles embodied in the Bretton Woods system. Yet the demand surprised third world delegates because they saw precedents for UNCTAD not in the IMF and World Bank but in the General Assembly and defunct ITO.(43) The group successfully countered the DMC proposal and make UNCTAD adopt two decision-making systems, both of which rejected weighted voting: decision by consensus and decision by majority rule of states. But the fact that the debate over decision-making rules could take place at all taught members of the group two lessons. They learned that the southern alliance had to agree explicitly upon decision-making principles. Moreover, they learned to consult among themselves about strategy and tactics as well as goals in order to assure that the south could use its majority effectively.(44)

In speeches at the first UNCTAD, southern officials equated the political principles they wanted to see the conference adopt with "democratic procedures."(45) This equation suggested that the resolutions of UNCTAD and similar meetings were "law" justified by popular sovereignty. (46) If the south had been concerned, first and foremost, with finding the shortest path to increased north-south cooperation, the "democratic procedures" slogan would have been a very poor choice. Many officials from those DMCs where one person, one vote was more or less the rule considered this third world concern with "democracy" to be a travesty. Few third world governments even attempted to approach democratic representation at home, and all shunned representing equal populations with one vote in international organizations.

However, if we ignore its immediate contribution to greater north-south misunderstanding and concentrate on its part in the development of the third world's mobilizing ideology, we can see the progressive role that the south's new concern with "democratic procedures" played. It made part of the south's unconsciously shared political views very conscious and very public. Arising at the time the Group of 77 itself was formed, the dispute over decision-making rules convinced group members that they needed to affirm a "political theory," a view of how decisions could and should be made. Developing such political ideas meant thinking about how the group's economic ideology could be made dominant. Even the little thought that went into quickly responding to the DMCs proposals with calls for more "democratic" means actually helped the south. Of course, majority votes in favor of third world proposals could hardly be expected to revolutionize the world economic system as long as the system's major supporters did not accept the legitimacy of majority rule. On the other hand, structured consensus formation could be used to reform the system fundamentally. DMCs would accept such procedures because the north retained its veto.

In promulgating new rules for "conciliation" at the first UNCTAD, the third world experimented with what turned out to be a successful means for making some of its views dominant.(47) More importantly, as a result of debate over political procedures, Group of 77 members, for the first time, became very aware that they really needed to test various political means and consciously repeat successfully employed ones, recognize the limits of their success, and consciously avoid repeating fruitless methods. By the end of the decade third world spokesmen knew that the systems of structured consensus building first attempted at UNCTAD I were an effective means of obtaining specific concessions from the developed nations but an ineffective means for achieving agreement on principles.(48)

In the years immediately following the first UNCTAD, the Group of 77 hardly built upon the political analysis it had so rapidly adopted in 1964. The group continued to work on the basis of "democratic" consensus formation with the major economic powers to come to agreements on specific concessions. The group tried to get decisions by majority rule when decision by consensus was impossible, but even by the second UNCTAD meeting in 1968 most LDC governments had started to distance themselves from the ineffective posturing that unenforceable majority rule decisions represented.(49)

Meanwhile, third world perceptions of the need to develop political links within the group convinced governments to make existing links more concrete. Between the first UNCTAD and the second, the group demonstrated the significance of its unity, and the fact that in certain contexts majority rule decisions could be effective, by its ability to unite U.N. aid programs and create the Industrial Development Organization (UNIDO) over the objection of DMC governments.(50) The Asian, African, and Latin American conferences of the Group of 77 prior to second UNCTAD resulted on unified regional positions. The group's meeting in Algiers prior to the conference easily resolved what differences there were in the regional plans. At UNCTAD II the group appointed designated spokesmen to argue their majority position.(51) Nonetheless, neither the majorities that the group bothered to muster behind its proposals, nor the consensus-making process, resulted in international agreement on fundamental issues.

After the second disappointing meeting of UNCTAD, the third world's political tactics became more complex, third world governments added to the notion of using "democratic means" to advance their position the idea that they should consciously attempt to influence elite and public opinion in the developed states. The group actually adopted this political tactic while under the influence of DMC elite opinion.

When former American defense secretary Robert McNamara began his presidency of the World Bank he called upon former Canadian prime minister Lester Pearson to form a commission and report to him on international development needs. Pearson chose Arthur Lewis and Roberto de Oliveria Campos along with five statesmen from the DMCs to join him. Their report, Partners in Development, ran through four popular printings in 1969 and 1970 after its first release in 1968.(52) The authors' proposals fundamentally agreed with the Group of 77's. The commission added a concern with establishing development related population programs that echoed proposals made by a number of group members but that had been rejected as part of the consensus of the group.(53) Likewise, the Pearson Commission expressed a concern for equalizing the distribution of wealth within developing nations. Governments of individual third world states had expressed such views, but the group had never collectively accepted them.(54) At the same time, the Pearson Commission affirmed a moral duty of the rich to aid the poor that was compatible with the third world views of states' economic rights and duties.

LDCs praised the Pearson Commission from the outset, although a number of governments demurred over the issue of birth control. Many third world U.N. representatives immediately adopted the simple political analysis the Pearson Commission report offered for the failure of previous international development efforts; they represented failures of "political will" on the part of governments, especially DMC governments.(55) The delegate from Cameroon expressed the southern view well when he argued that "political will" had created the Marshall Plan and "political will" could still create effective international cooperation for economic development.(56)

To energize DMC political will in 1968, the third world suggested mounting a campaign to influence DMC public opinion.(57) In 1969 Tanzania proposed that legislators from the Group of 77 attempt to influence fellow parliamentarians in developed countries to change their governments' foreign policies.(58) The General Assembly's extensive Declaration on Social Progress and Development of 1969 reflect both proposals. In addition, as part of the campaign to change northern opinion, the General Assembly charged the Secretary General with disseminating the declaration as widely as possible.(59)

Events since 1969 may make us think the third world was naive to believe that public opinion in the north mattered. No theory which considered public opinion important appears to have guided the one set of third world actions that actually made the most people in the north aware of southern views — i.e., the unpopular OPEC price increases. Yet in the U.N. debates of 1968 and 1969 only one member of the group, Sudan, argued that an emphasis on influencing DMC public opinion was misguided.(60)

Events in 1968 made the third world belief in the effectiveness of public and legislative opinion very reasonable. An American president had refused to run for another term when it became clear to him that the public and Congress would no longer support his foreign policy approach. Mass demonstrations almost toppled the French government. Moreover, the liberal western political theories that a majority of third world leaders had learned and still accepted, in theory if not in practice, identified the opinions and goals of mass publics and their representatives as the proper source of foreign policy, and, much more importantly, as the actual source of foreign policy in those states with active liberal political institutions, the DMCs.(61)

Despite these good reasons for attempting to influence DMC opinion, third world attempts to energize northern political will remained small operations throughout the sixties. The only resources committed to the effort were those of the U.N. agencies, the Secretary General's office and UNCTAD in particular. Yet this small-scale expression of concern with influencing DMC opinion had effects on the emerging DMC ideology beyond the simple fact that it happened to be one of the earliest bits of political theory the Group of 77 collectively and consciously adopted. Like moves toward strengthening the alliance itself, attempting to influence the attitudes of people within DMCs required LDC supporters to present their opinions about the world economy in a more unified and coherent, and thus more convincing, form. It required third world leaders to make their ideology even more explicit and distinct.

More New Economic Issues for the South

However, the real diversity of interests within the third world mitigated against the development of a more explicit, coherent, and convincing ideology in the late sixties. That diversity had been made greater by new economic issues. The Bretton Woods system's heyday of income and trade growth affected different third world states in different ways. While the Group of 77 was able to respond to the new issues by creating hypothetical programs that would have provided some benefits to every third world state if they were enacted, the group had trouble finding ways to logically link all the new programs they proposed in a single, coherent economic policy analysis. The group could easily blame some of the new problems on the Bretton Woods system; analysis of those problems could be easily integrated into the ideology. Those problems that could not be so easily blamed on the system were much harder to coherently link to the rest of the ideology.

The increasing lack of coherence in the ideology's policy analysis became all the more problematic because the south's solidarity behind a single interpretation of the economic rights and duties of states began to break. In the late sixties had enlarged the third world alliance to included governments that defined the economic duties of wealthy states as responsibilities incumbent upon them because of their past or current colonialism. Potentially, this opinion could have wrecked the ideological foundation of the third world alliance by opening up ethical questions which had be closed for years. Instead, members of the group simply stopped reiterating one part of the ethical foundation of their analysis. They continued to discuss the the economic rights of states in general terms as well as the specific duties of wealthy states, including a duty they newly agreed was incumbent upon colonizers, like Portugal and South Africa, to compensate for their colonialism. But, in the late 1960s the south ignore its older argument that the general, permanent duty of every state to unique economic development of other states provided the major reason why material aid could be demanded from the wealthy.

While members of the Group of 77 never publically confronted each other with demands to debate their different moral codes the disagreement over principles reinforced newly developing conflicts of interest within the alliance. Poorer LDCs supported one ethic; richer LDCs supported another. Without a unifying view of the economic rights and duties of states it became hard for LDCs to argue that all the new problems separate states experienced in the 1960s should be with under the same agenda. This reassured those supporters of the existing economic system who believed that third world calls for a "new" economic system were inherently incoherent. Even if, as the third world argued, there were some unfortunate unintended consequences resulting from the operation of the Bretton Woods system, those problems appeared to be localized ones that in no way changed the evaluation of the Bretton Woods system offered by its strongest advocates: Under the system world trade and economic growth had expanded like they never had before, and they had done so at the expense of no nation.

Of course, third world states measured the costs of the Bretton Woods system not against systems that had gone before but against the expected costs of the reformed system they wanted to see created. In those terms, they could argue that the actual system had unexpected costs that only some states had borne.

Throughout the sixties third world governments linked their analyses of the disadvantages of the IMF and World Bank. Functionally, both institutions seemed the same to many hard-pressed governments. Both provided loans that could be used to meet government expenses. Likewise, third world leaders thought of the bilateral aid systems in the same terms. The bilateral aid systems functioned as part of the world economic order, the Bretton Woods system broadly understood. In the sixties four new effects of the postwar aid and monetary order came to bother third world governments.

As we have seen, those less industrialized countries that actually did receive loans for development in the fifties had trouble repaying their debts, especially when that had taking out short term loans to finance the sort of infrastructure projects the south most demanded in the fifties. Such projects showed no immediate profit and mounting debt became even more difficult to pay back since third world trade remained stagnant.(62)

At the opposite end of the spectrum of wealth, the poorest LDCs felt the aid system led to the increasing relative impoverishment of the LLDCs relative to other states. LLDCs received a small proportion of available aid. The World Bank's understandable concern with its own financial health meant that prior to the creation of the IDA it loaned mostly to states that could easily pay their debts, states that were relatively wealthy already.(63)

Third world governments identified a similar problem associated with world liquidity. Because the U.S. dollar had been the world's most accepted currency since the war the U.S. could expand global liquidity accumulating trade deficits for goods Americans purchased abroad. Consequently, the initial benefits of expanding the amount of money in global circulation went to the United States, the wealthiest state; and because the U.S.'s most important trade partners were DMCs, the multiplier effects of increasingly global liquidity were extended almost exclusively to the DMCs, thus, in the third world view, increasing the relative poverty of the LDCs. (64) When the IMF moved toward creating an internationally managed means for expanding global liquidity in the latter half of the decade ·— through IMF Special Drawing Rights (SDRs) — IMF member allocated those funds on the basis of the IMF quotas used to compute voting weights. This system had almost the same effect as the pure dollar standard. It gave most of the initial advantages of increasing the global money supply to the already wealthy regions.(65)

Third world states first raised one final, related issue in the sixties. Those third world states that had taken advantage of bilateral aid began to draw attention to the economic strings attached to economic aid in the same way that they first had brought attention to political strings in the 1950s. Requirements that aid be used to purchase goods from donor countries — goods that could often be purchased at lower prices elsewhere — especially bothered them. Beyond the simple economic disadvantages of these arrangements when compared to the multilateral aid systems the south had advocated since the forties, the economic strings attached to bilateral aid increased the recipient economy's dependence on that of the donor.

As we have seen, the third world's solutions to the new aid problems they discovered in the sixties were similar to the solutions they offered to similar problems in the fifties. Because they blamed those aid problems on the Bretton Woods system, they simply used their existing principles and plans for an alternative system in order to understand and suggest solutions to the new problems. Under their long standing principles, the south emphasized the special responsibility of all states to aid the LLDCs and defined the minimal material responsibility of the developed nations with the aid target of 1 percent of GNP. In addition, the south acted to assure that the U.N.'s Special Fund and technical assistance programs would be coordinated and directed toward third world industrialization, thus creating a model for the multilateral aid system the south desired.

To third world leaders, inadequacies in the existing system also explained the new monetary problems they experienced. In again blaming Bretton Woods third world leaders, sought solutions to the new monetary problems in slight amendments to their own emerging vision of an alternative system. They talked about expanding the IMF so that it became, in part, an aid agency. They proposed that any new international liquidity created by the IMF be allocated to states on the basis of some measure of economic need.(66) This proposal went back to ideas on the subject advanced in the 1950s by Maxwell Stamp, the British director of the IMF, and from there back to Lord Keynes's bag of hypothetical economic tricks and to the alternative vision of the postwar system which had been the basis for the third world's own policy analysis.(67) The south justified the proposed "Link" in the same way they justified other aid programs, as a way for wealthy states to fufill their duty to materially aid the economic development plans chosen by those less advantaged.

Supporters of the Bretton Woods system never denied that the system in part "caused" the four new aid and monetary problems that third world states experienced in the sixties. Supporters did deny that the things that "caused" the problems were problems in themselves. Instead, they saw them as necessary elements in any truly workable aid and money regimes. The problems experienced by the richest and poorest LDCs were unfortunate, but, Bretton Woods system advocates argued, no state or private investor would give development loans if they did not expect them to be repaid. True, supporters argued, the unique role of the U.S. in expanding world liquidity had never been carefully planned, but the fact that it (somewhat surprisingly) worked was reason enough to maintain the principle it embodied of expanding liquidity to nations on the basis of their economic might. Likewise, many leaders saw tying aid to repurchase agreements as a small domestic political price that rich countries had to pay in order to offer any aid at all. To supporters of Bretton Woods, these were less problems than facts, and certainly they were not the basis for new grievances with the existing order.

Third world spokesmen in the sixties did not try to respond to northern doubts about the reality of the new aid and money problems the south faced. They might have been able to do so by explaining how the emerging hypothetical alternative to Bretton Woods would insure things like investor confidence and popular support for aid from within DMCs, but it had been hard enough to integrate these new issues into the third world's own prior understanding. Yet these aid and money issues were easier to integrate into the southern consensus than another set of problems third world states experienced in the sixties, ones that could not be blamed so easily on the Bretton Woods system. Had third world officials been more willing to grant the Bretton Woods system its successes they might have been able to see this final set of new problems as like their new aid and money problems: unintended byproducts of the postwar system's operation.

The increasingly liberal trade system that the postwar regimes advanced provided opportunities for large firms to invest abroad with greater ease than ever before. Of course, individually, almost every country around the world also encouraged such investment. By the end of the sixties, nevertheless, most third world states expressed some dissatisfactions with their relationships to what the U.N. Secretariat had dubbed in mid-decade "transnational corporations," TNCs.(68) Third world representatives complained of profits being repatriated in excess of the funds brought into the country by foreign firms, and of the difficulties in assuring that foreign investors followed the guidelines set out in national development plans.(69) While third world spokesmen did not try to explain the rise of TNCs, the southern ethic suggested where solutions to their problems with TNCs might be found. It pointed toward finding the means to assure that the self-defined interests of states remained sovereign in relations with foreign firms. But the 1960s closed not only before the south developed a shared analysis of the rise of TNCs but also before they even came to share views about how to combat the problems foreign investment created. The south turned over the problem of developing such analysis to the United Nations secretariats.(70)

A somewhat similar problem, "the brain drain," also became a third world issue in the sixties. The successes of the liberal international system helped make it possible for highly skilled people from poorer countries to find and move to jobs in the richest parts of the world. In the sixties third world governments saw the brain drain as a problem, but the Group of 77 offered no analysis of its origins or specific programs for eliminating it or its effects.(71)

A sort of obverse of the brain drain became a new issue in the sixties as well. Skilled people left poorer countries to go to wealthier ones, but that transfer was not balanced by the transfer of skills and technology from the rich to the poor. The postwar international economic system treated technological innovations like any other property. Governments of poorer countries could have access to new technology only through the market, by buying patent rights or encouraging the owners of those rights to invest in the poor country. In the sixties, however, before the role of the Bretton Woods system as a protector of existing property rights had been openly and loudly debated, the third world raised their concerns about increasing "technology transfers" without linking those concerns to specific condemnations of existing regimes. Rather, third world governments proposed the existence of a new "right to the fruits of technology," a proposal to treat know-how as a common good, a collective resource that no individual could claim an ultimate property right to control.(72) In later years discussion of this view would open up the north-south debate over limits on the roles of international economic management organizations that was never opened at the UNCTAD conferences or at other meetings in the sixties. In the sixties, beyond the simple affirmation that this new right — an extension of the rights and duties of states — existed, the third world had little more to say about easing the transfer of technology.

The TNC, brain drain, and technology transfer issues would have contributed little to the increasing incoherence of the third world's "new" ideology had the Group of 77 been able to remain solidly behind the view of states economic rights and duties they had long shared, the ideas that justified the first southern views on these new issues. But the Group of 77 did not remain solidly behind its oldest principles at the end of the 1960s. Paradoxically, decolonization, which increased the number of states in the third world, proved the greatest threat to the alliance's unity. Unity could only be restored, in the short run, by deemphasizing the older principles.

Governments of the newer states, mostly African, explained the duties of developed states to make extra efforts on behalf of the globe's poor in a markedly different way than older members of the third world alliance explained the same duty. The more radical African governments in the early sixties, following those of Guinea and Ghana, consistently spoke of duties imposed on wealthy states by the fact that they had once exploited their colonies.(73) The former colonizers owed a debt to the colonized. Africans suggested many historical precedents for such notions, including the compensation paid by the American government to former slaves, the more significant twentieth century precedent of the war debts paid by those who lost the world wars, and the debts paid by the Federal Republic of Germany to Jewish citizens and to the state of Israel.(74) Franz Fanon's The Wretched of the Earth, published in the early sixties, expressed this view well:

When we hear the head of a European state declare with his hand on his heart that he must come to the aid of poor underdeveloped people we do not tremble with gratitude. Quite the contrary; we say to ourselves: "It's a just reparation which will be paid to us."(75)

During the sixties this theme was taken up by representatives of many new states both within and outside of Africa in such a way that latent divisions among third world states became apparent.

If this ethic of reparations were to be accepted in lieu of the notion of permanent states' economic rights and duties, then either many of the early members of the third world movement, including the Latin American states, would have no claim to aid from wealthy-countries, or else the relevant historical period for assessing debts would have to be pushed back to the beginning of the modern world economy. In the later case the analytical distinction in the third world ideology that colonialism was the basic early cause of underdevelopment would be given moral force as well. Few nations accepted this particular resolution of the differences between newer and older members of the alliance in the sixties. Latin American delegates to international meetings, in particular, almost never used the historical argument from colonialism as a justification for the duties of wealthy states.(76)

In peculiar contrast, some wealthy states used the restitution ethic to justify their lack of action-in support of the LDCs. By the 1968 second UNCTAD the socialist states of eastern Europe, which had appeared to be so cooperative to the third world at UNCTAD I, had adopted the restitution ethic. They said that their duties differed from those of the DMCs because as socialist states they neither had been colonizers nor had they exploited poorer countries through the instruments of neocolonialism. (77) Neocolonialism, after all, had been linked only to capitalism by the popularizer of the concept, Kwame Nkrumah.(78)

After they learned the position that the socialists would take, Group of 77 members reunited behind at least that part of their old ethic that said all rich states had duties to poor ones. The Charter of Algiers, agreed to before UNCTAD II, reflected that part of the earlier stand without ever mentioning reparations for colonialism.(79)

This charter makes specific demands upon the socialist states. Nonetheless, it devotes no space to outlining the general ethic for international economic relations. In one sense, this lack of the usual restatement of the general ethic could be interpreted as just reflecting a recognition that the principles of the new economic order had already been stated at the first UNCTAD and voting on them again at the second would just be an example of a fruitless use of the Group of 77's majority. Now was the time to "move away from the stage of deliberation to the plane of practical action. "(80) But, by not explicitly restating the older understanding of the economic rights and duties of states and saying that they were the only fundamental principles for the new order, the Group of 77 left room for some of its members to argue for aid on the basis of the restitution ethic.

Two factors continued to assure that the dispute over the restitution ethic would generate further developments in the south's ideology. First, most of the LDCs to which the ethic appealed were also LLDCs, those that were the most dependent on exports of commodities that sold in what they believed to be particularly wild, fluctuating markets, and those that received the least foreign aid. This was the group of countries some scholars in the north started to call the "fourth world," the poorest nations whose economic interests differed from those of the wealthier third world states. The restitution ethic symbolized the particularly severe problems of the least advantaged. Second, the ideological predilictions of many of those people sympathetic to the LDCs in rich countries made them more sympathetic to the restitution argument than to the one based upon assumed permanent rights and duties of states. Jean Paul Sartre exemplifies this northern view in his preface to The Wretched of the Earth where he argues that the shame Europeans feel when confronted with knowledge of the worst horrors of colonialism would make them accept Fanon's view that restitution was essential.(81)

Yet at the end of the sixties, when third world states first mounted an effort to influence public and elite opinion in the north, they did not rely on the powerful restitution ethic because not all third world states shared it. The 1969 Declaration on Social Progress and Development, which was supposed to be so widely distributed, exemplifies the moral compromises the alliance had to reach at the end of the decade. (82) Its second and third articles lay out the by then traditional rights of states. Its first, fourth, fifth, sixth, and seventh articles lay out specific egalitarian rights of individuals and families. The bulk of the rest of the document lays out only specific duties of governments, some of governments in developed countries, some of governments in developing countries. Article 26 specifies that restitution for aggression and illegal occupation must be paid by the aggressor state. But this article does not say that back payments for colonialism that had ended was necessary. All the specific UNCTAD principles of 1964 are included as specific duties. What is missing in this program, as in the Charter of Algiers, is an overarching article explaining all these duties of developed states under a single justification -- either as specific instances of a duty to aid the unique economic development of the neediest or as specific instances of a duty to provide reparations for colonialism.

In some ways, of course, this loose definition of the duties of developed states, this lack of an overarching article, contributed to the later success of the ideology in attracting supporters in the developed world. Third world silence on the ultimate moral ground of northern duties under their new economic order allowed northern supporters to choose their own justification. Like Sartre, they could emphasize a duty based on historical rights violated during colonialism. Like Pearson, they could emphasize a general, ahistorical duty of wealthy states. Nevertheless, the person in the developed countries who was not yet sympathetic to the plight of the LDCs could find as many contradictions in the late-1960s version of the third world position as sympathizers could find justifications for creating a new economic order.

This incoherence in the third world view at the end of the decade made it difficult for those who first observed global economic meetings then to see the "third world" as a reality. Identifying a "third world ideology" from a single meeting at the end of the sixties would be just as difficult. Just as the new order ideology had been temporarily lost in the cooperative north-south dialogue at the beginning of the "development decade," the disagreements within the south at decade's end made statements of their common position increasingly vague, abstract, and indistinct. Observation of the common third world position at any point in the decade other than its very beginning and end would yield an entirely different picture. The new order ideology remained distinct throughout most of the sixties.

It passed through two separate stages of growth just as significant as the first stage it had passed through while the Bretton Woods system was forming. The second and third stages, like the first one, were characterized by fundamentally new issues that members of the third world alliance were learning to apprehend in the same way. During the whole decade southern adherents to the new order ideology reiterated their consensus about the economic problems that the Bretton Woods system left unresolved and added to it an analysis of what to do about new problems that the operation of the Bretton Woods system helped create. In the first half of the decade, the second stage in the development of the ideology, only these new problems related to the system's operation served to trigger ideological innovation.

The second half of the decade, the third stage in the ideology's development, was more eventful. Adherents consciously defined their collective political identity, made the further specification of their shared views a conscious goal, and began to develop strategies to make their views dominant. Of course the third world had a collective identity by 1959, but conscious reflection on that identity, which was needed before further specification of shared views could be made a conscious goal, only came with the formation of the Group of 77 and the subsequent development of political strategy which marked the third stage.

The fact that reflection upon their collective identity had become commonplace for group members by the end of the decade made it possible for them to consciously redefine that identity in order to assure group unity. When the ideological conflicts between the richer and poorer developing states appeared at the end of the decade members of the group could make their shared views more amorphous to accommodate the conflicting views. That made the group's ideology look less coherent. But a more significant commitment to consciously developing a shared position remained the foundation for the group's stated views, even at the end of the sixties. Reinforced by strategic commitment to group unity that developed as a conscious political tactic in the late sixties, the ability to reflect upon and redefine what it meant to be "the third world" allowed the alliance to rapidly turn their position, which was temporarily amorphous at the end of the sixties, into the much more coherent and concrete calls for a New International Economic Order that dominated the seventies.

Notes

(1)Patino speaking at Second, 18, Oct. 4, 1963, p. 27; Sidney Weintraub, "After the U.N. Trade Conference: Lessons and Portents," Foreign Affairs 43 (Oct. 1964): 46.

(2)GATT, International Trade 1966 (Geneva: 1967).

(3)Quoted by the Indian delegate at Second, 13, Oct. 18, 1958, p. 45.

(4) See e.g. the Economist's editorials cited in chapter 1, note 95.

(5)This was a Bolivian suggestion, Second, 12, Oct. 27, 1958, p. 87.

(6)GATT, International Trade 1960 (Geneva: 1961), pp. 7-10. See also Undersecretary de Seynes's report on trade, Second, 15, Oct. 12, 1960, pp. 7-9.

(7Ts'audi Arabia, Second, 15, Oct. 18, 1960, p. 100.

(8)Colombia, Second, 15, Oct. 28, 1960, p. 114.

(9)Raul Prebisch, "The Economic Development of Latin America and Its Principal Problems," Economic Bulletin for Latin America 7 (Feb. 1962): 1-22.

(10)On the third world view see Mexico, Second, 15, Oct. 28, 1960, p. 110 and Turkey, Second, 15, Nov. 1, 1960, p. 123.

(11)See the appeal by Uruguay to U.N. members to live up to Charter duties by instituting "equitable treatment," Second, 15, Oct. 27, 1960, p. 87.

(12)G. Aforka Nwekwe, Harmonization of African Foreign Policies 195-1975: The Political Economy of African Diplomacy (Boston: Boston Univ. African Studies Center), p. 94-107.

(13)Selected Documents, Belgrade Declaration of Non-Aligned Countries, Sept. 6, 1961, p. 9.

(14)Second, 16, Oct. 20, 1961, p. 76.

(15)GATT, International Trade 1961 (Geneva: 1962), pp. 20-28.

(16)John A. Pincus, Trade, Aid, and Development (New York: Council on Foreign Relations, 1967), pp. 126-27.

(17) Branislav Gosovic, UNCTAD Conflict and Compromise (Leiden: A. W. Sijthoff, 1972), pp. 15-21.

(18)E.g., Tunisia, Second 15, Nov. 1, 1960.

(19)Second, 17, Oct. 17, 1962, p. 72. This was first suggested in the U.N. by Krishna Menon, Second, 15, Nov. 11, 1960, p. 195.

(20)See e.g., Chile, Second, 18, Oct. 16, 1963, p. 106.

(21)Second, 17, Oct. 4, 1962, pp. 19-20.

(22)Joshua, 9:21.

(23)Selected Documents, Charter of Alta Gracia, Mar. 7, 1964, pp. 29-31.

(24)Selected Documents, Niamey Resolution on the U.N. Conference on Trade and Development, Dec. 13, 1963, pp. 20-21.

(25)See the short intellectual history in the annex to the group of experts report on the structure of the United Nations system, A New United Nations Structure for Global Economic Cooperation (New York: United Nations, 1975), pp. 61-69.

(26)Second, 18, Oct. 8, 1963, p. 57.

(27)Raul Prebisch, Towards a New Trade Policy for Development (New York: UNCTAD, 1964); on the report as the conference agenda see A. D. Friedeberg, The United Nations Conference on Trade and Development: The Theory of the Peripheral Economy at the Centre of International Discussions (Rotterdam: Rotterdam Univ. Press, 1969), pp. 70-84.

(28)Compare Friedeberg's discussion above with the UNCTAD principles in Selected Documents, UNCTAD I: Final Act and Recommendations, June 15, 1964, pp. 43-50.

(29)Selected_Documents, UNCTAD I: Final Act and Recommendations, June 15, 1964, pp. 43-47.

(30)Weintraub, p. 52.

(31)Hence Patino's remark quoted at the head of the chapter.

(32)Gosovic, p. 164.

(33)Ibid., p. 165.

(34)Urie Bronfenbrenner, "The Mirror Image in Soviet-American Relations: A Social Psychologist's Report," Journal of Social Issues 17, no. 3 (1961):45-56.

(35)Gosovic, p. 166, note 42.

(36)See, for example, the general argument about the United States in Stephen D. Krasner, Defending the National Interest (Princeton: Princeton Univ. Press, 1978).

(37)Margaret Garritsen de Vries, The IMF 1966-71: The System Under Stress, vol. 1 (Washington: IMF, 1976), pp. 269-76.

(3S)Explicit GATT acceptance of this notion was quite straightforward by the mid-1970s. See Selected Documents, Tokyo Declaration, Sept. 14, 1973, pp. 444-49.

(39)GATT, International Trade 1965 (Geneva: 1966), p. 19.

(40)Weintraub, p. 48.

(41 )Friedeberg summarizes Haberler's criticisms, pp. 53-56.

(42)Selected Pocamente, Joint Declaration of the Group of 77 at UNCTAD I, June 15, 1964, p, 33.

(43)Gosovic, pp. 52-57.

{44)See the penultimate paragraph of the Joint Declaration, Selected Documents, p. 34.

(4 5)See the affirmation in Selected Documents, Cairo Declaration of the Non-Aligned Countries, Oct. 10, 1964, p. 94.

(46)See Gosovic's analysis, p. 57.

(47)On the creation of these consensus or "conciliation" procedures see Gosovic, pp. 56-57, and see pp. 171-72 on concessions the south obtained.

(48)Ibid., p. 172,

(49)Consider, e.g., the Nigerian statement in the Second Committee during planning for UNCTAD II. Instead of calling for new principles, the way Nigerian's had when they helped lead the call for UNCTAD in the early part of the decade, he emphasized conciliation procedures and demanded that the UNCTAD agenda be very specific, Second, 22, Oct. 4, 1967, p. 16.

(50)Selected Documents General Assembly Resolution 2152: United Nations Industrial Development Program, Nov. 17, 1966, p. 843. UNIDO coordinates policy with the U.N. Development Program and the U.N. Capital Development fund which provides multilateral aid through voluntary contributions by U.N. members. The capital development fund was created at the same time as UNIDO.

(51)Selected Documents, Charter of Algiers, Oct. 24, 1967, pp. 135-45, c.f. the Nigerian speech, Second, 22, Oct. 4, 1967, p. 16.

(52)Lester Pearson, ed., Partners in Development (New York: Praeger, 1969).

(53)Ibid., pp. 56-57.

(54)Ibid., pp. 7-10.

(55)Ibid., pp. 3-32.

(56)Second, 23, Oct. 14, 1968, p. 7.

(57)Indonesia, Second, 23, Oct. 11, 1968, p. 2.

(58)Second, 24, Oct. 16, 1969, p. 30.

(59)Selected Documents, General Assembly Resolution 2543: Implementation of the Declaration on Social Progress and Development, Dec. 11, 1969, p. 855.

(60)Second, 24, Oct. 15, 1969, p. 19.

(61)See Chinweizu's emotional account of these beliefs among members of Africa's elite in the independence generation, "The Cult of Liberal Democracy," The West and the Rest of Us (New York: Random House, 19751, pp. 234-46.

(62)At the 1966 meeting of the Second Committee India forecast that debt servicing payments for the third world would be greater than incoming aid in less than fifteen years. Second, Oct. 13, 1966, p. 20.

(63)See chapter 1, note 91.

(64)The early discussions in the U.N. along these lines took place in 1966. See the Syrian speech, Second, 21, Oct. 14, 1966, p. 69.

(65)See the Algerian speech, Second, 24, Oct. 20, 1969, p. 61.

(66)This proposal was contained in an IMF report discussed by the delegate from Sudan, Second, 21, Oct. 17, 1966, p. 85.

(67)An Economist editorial of July 27, 1963 issue (p. 34), suggests increasing global liquidity simply by giving needed aid to poorer states. The editors distinguish this proposal slightly from Stamp's. Stamp would have the actual level of international trade determine the level of increased liquidity in the system, although an aid element would be introduced by giving much of that new liquidity to poorer states.

(68)By Undersecretary de Seynes reporting to the Second Committee, Second, 20, Oct. 5, 1965, p. 7.

(69)Cuba had raised these issues at the beginning of the decade, Second,. 15, Oct. 27, I960, p. 94, but few other states mentioned TNCs in the U.N. until the late sixties.

(70)In 1968 the Asian Regional Conference of the International Labor Organization urged the organization's staff to address questions of TNCs. In the same year U.S. members of the organization urged a similar study. Thus that organization studied the relationship between TNCs and social policy before UNCTAD or the Economic and Social Council did. The later began their work in 1972. U.N. Department of Social and Economic Affairs, Multinational Corporations in World Development (New York: United Nations, 1973), pp. 116-17.

(71)The first U.N. discussion of the brain drain was triggered by Iran, Second, 22, Oct. 15, 1967, p. 50.

(72)Oscar Schacter, Sharing the World's Resources (New York: Columbia Univ. Press, 1977), pp. 105-24. Schacter's primary concern is with the broader legal and ethical questions suggested by the issue.

(73)Ibid., pp. 20-21.

(74)Ghana, Second, 15, Oct. 20, 1960, p. 35; Guinea, Second, 16, Oct. 18, 1961, p. 49.

(75)Franz Fanon, The Wretched of the Earth (New York: Grove Press, 1968), p. 102.

(76)Latin American delegates rarely use the argument that wealthy nations were obligated to repay for colonialism. They do argue that a history of colonialism is a cause of underdevelopment and that the wealth of the developed states obligates the developed states to aid the underdeveloped.

(77)See Gosovic, p. 166, and the strong statement of this position in Selected Documents, Joint Statement of the Socialist Countries on the Second Development Decade and Social Progress, Sept. 21, 1970, pp. 204-207.

(78)Kwame Nkrumah, Neocolonialism, The Last Stage of Imperialism (London: Nelson, 1965).

(79)The Charter of Algiers eschewed the moral justifications found in previous third world statements and replaced them with a discussion of third world poverty and the failure of previous international efforts to reduce it.

(80)Selected Documents, Charter of Algiers, Oct. 24, 1967, p. 136.

(81)Jean Paul Sartre, Preface to Fanon's The Wretched of the Earth, pp. 7-34.

(82)Selected Documents, General Assembly Resolution 2542: Declaration on Social Progress and Development, Dec. 11, 1969, pp. 850-54.

Afterword: How Ideas Can Help Resolve the North-South Conflict

Any historical study leads to conclusions that can be documented and to others that cannot. This afterword contains my more speculative conclusions about the new order ideology. They cannot be supported by a weight of evidence because they do not concern what the ideology has been; they concern what it might become. I believe the NIEO ideology might someday contribute knowledge needed to resolve the current north-south conflict.

In abstract terms, the conflict will be resolved when the Bretton Woods system or its successor learns to deal with the south's economic problems as well as it deals with the north's. If we can say that the the new order ideology performs functions of "consciousness" for the third world, we can similarly say that those who act for the Bretton Woods system share a consciousness, of which the dominant ideology is part. What Deutsch's framework would have us call the "consciousness" of that system just equals what other scholars would call the "complex regime" containing the Bretton Woods institutions. In that regime the dominant ideology provides rules and guides for behavior and the Bretton Woods institutions help keep the regime open to new information. Understood in that way, as Ernst Haas illustrates, a regime is the locus of a capacity to learn how to manage fundamentally new problems even while it remains the consciousness consulted by those who manage a particular global issue.(l) I believe, then, that the new order ideology and the experience of its southern advocates can help the postwar management system learn to deal effectively with the south's problems. That would transform the postwar institutions and require transformation of the dominant ideology.

Two equally speculative arguments suggest the new order ideology's capacity to contribute knowledge needed to manage global economic problems more effectively. One highlights the dilemmas third world advocates often face as a result of their contradictory positions in world society and within their home countries. According to one of the doyens of the policy sciences, Duncan MacRae, people in such contradictory roles are likely to produce positive social innovations.(2) The NIEO ideology's third world advocates live at the intersection between the cultures of the world's wealthy and the cultures of its most impoverished. They try consciously to resolve the contradictions between the two. More than any other group, they are likely to develop ways to resolve those contradictions.

In an entirely different way, the simple fact that NIEO advocates have been opposing the current system for almost forty years may have given them some of the knowledge the system itself needs. Immanuel Wallerstein, who began his career by looking for the commonalities among all the different successful nationalist movements in Africa, claims that the weaker party in any protracted struggle will know more about their relationship to the stronger than the stronger party will.(3) The NIEO's advocates may know some things about the world economy that adherents to the dominant ideology have never learned.

Whatever wisdom about the world economy the third world may have acquired in its forty year conflict with the north, however, will not influence actual intergovernmental economic management until north and south agree upon their common interests. The current focus of the north-south conflict over the role of existing specialized agencies within the process of global negotiations may help. If both sides treat this disagreement as a substantive debate, and therefore try to convince the other side rather than to get it to make concessions, the result could be agreement on a formula defining the common north-south interests that both sides want international institutions to serve.

Luckily, neither north nor south has anything to lose in this debate. They cannot even lose face by being convinced of the other's position. The north need not be worried about being convinced of the south's position because the south's position on the proper role of intergovernmental economic management institutions remains one of the few incoherent parts of the new order ideology. The south need not worry about being convinced by the north; the north's current position on the subject makes no more sense.

The dominant ideology holds that intergovernmental economic management institutions exist only to do things that no state can do by itself. On this north and south agree. Neither fully accepts the lesson Keynes taught, that total subjection of international institutions to the will of one or many states would make such management impossible. Northerners just argue that international institutions must be subject to the interests of their dominant member states only, while the third world demands that international institutions be subject to the will of all states.

North and south will disagree over what common interest international institutions should have some autonomous responsibility to serve. Nonetheless, both northern and southern views will change if they debate the issue. Those views have to change, even if only to frame coherent opposing positions. That could get each side into a habit of changing its views in order to facilitate resolution of the conflict. If that were to happen, the last pages of the history of the south's new order ideology could be written about how it changed through time to resolve the north-south conflict, rather than to perpetuate it.

That has not happened yet. As I finish writing this afterword, in July 1983, north and south look as far apart as ever. UNCTAD VI has just ended after illustrating many of the themes in the last pages of this history of the NIEO ideology. The south came to UNCTAD VI with a set of proposals for "emergency" assistance to the third world, (4) proposals influenced by the opinions of their northern supporters on the Brandt Commission whose second report argued the need for such a crisis program even if it meant postponing global agreement on more fundamental reforms.(5) The northern states rejected even this seemingly moderate short-term proposal.

While southern delegates to UNCTAD VI may have thought that they had moderated their views by ending their calls for immediate creation of the NIEO and by adopting some of the views of their northern supporters, the major northern nations did not see it that way. The U.S. and its closest allies argued that the south's emergency program was too costly and that UNCTAD did not even have the authority to discuss it since the program involved much more than trade matters. Those northern governments still on the far side of ul Haq's philosophical bridge that I discuss in chapter 4 even denied the south's analysis of the current situation in the world economy. The most conservative northern states contended that while the economic health of the LDCs depended on that of the developed nations, the opposite was not at all true; the south's economic well-being was peripheral to that of the north.

The north's position at UNCTAD VI will not be its final word. Significantly, the day after the UNCTAD meetings ended two of the most important economic policy makers in the U.S. contradicted the analysis their government had been loudly defending for a month. The head of the American Council of Economic Advisors to the President and the Chairman of the Federal Reserve both argued that the economic health of some third world states, those with large debts, was indeed crucial to all developed countries.(6) That change in tune hardly means that the U.S. has accepted the significance of every third world country's economy or that the U.S. would be willing to conduct any substantive negotiations with the south in forums like UNCTAD, but the new U.S. argument was, in fact, the same one the Brandt Commission's second report had made. That position, in turn, provides a basis for substantive north-south discussions of common interests.

The south's UNCTAD VI position will not be its final word either, although I would not want to predict what lessons the south will draw from that meeting. Third world governments may decide that their recent strategy of showing more consideration for northern interests has been failure. The south may come to berate the Brandt Commission and other nongovernmental allies for suggesting common north-south interests that the most powerful northern governments failed to see. The south may move from its strategy of negotiation and from its growing interest in substantive debate with the north.

If the south does move away from its recent strategy the, NIEO ideology probably will contribute nothing to the resolution of the north-south conflict for some time. Now, the conflict can be resolved only through substantive debate. Given the difference in economic power between north and south, each round of simple bargaining based on exchanged concessions merely replicates the existing divisions between rich and poor and the conflict inherent in them. The path away from substantive debate will lead to a longer history for the NIEO ideology as third world governments transform their views in order to deal with their continuing conflict with the north.

Notes

(1)Ernst Haas, "Words Can Hurt You; or, Who Said What to Whom About Regimes," International Organization 36 (Spring 1982): 242.

(2)Duncan MacRae, The Social Function of Social Science (New Haven: Yale Univ. press, 1976), pp. 277-78.

T3)Immanuel Wallerstein, The Modern World-System (New York: Academic Press, 1974), p. 14.

(4)New York Times, July 3, 1983, p. 1.

(5) Independent Commission on International Development, Common Crisis (Cambridge: MIT Press, 1983).

(6)New York Times, July 5, 1983, p. 1.